But the issue here is that there are no
rules. Remember, your job while overseas
is to break the law. Your job is to
convince people to commit espionage for
you. Your job is to get people to give
you classified information or protected
information. It's not to to it's not to
disrupt human
trafficking. But you have to go into
this situation with your own set of
moral values. You have to know what the
right thing to do is because
headquarters isn't going to tell you.
They're not going to say, "Oh, remember
uh employee rule number 305 says you
can't provide child
prostitutes." You have to know in your
heart what's right and what's wrong.
But that's up to you. That's up to the
individual. So, if you've got somebody
that just doesn't have a real good moral
compass, they just don't find true north
on their compass and they want that
information, they're going to do
whatever they need to do to get it.
That's exactly right. And sometimes
there are there are employees who can't
turn it off. You know, every 10 years or
so, you'll see in the Washington Post or
the New York Times that a CIA employee
almost always an operations officer has
been arrested for sexual assault or for
embezzlement or something like that
because they just don't have a moral
compass. I remember one of my uh station
chiefs telling me early on in my career,
"Never lie to security, finance, or
medical. They're the three offices that
could ruin your life."
Well, it's actually more than that.
Never lie to yourself. Never lie to your
station chief, right? You've got to
bounce ideas off of somebody to give you
a second opinion. Because if somehow you
wake up one morning and you think it's
all right to put a roofy in in a woman's
drink at a cocktail party and assault
her afterwards, which has happened, then
you need somebody to to check your
thought process. You kind of have the
same process. Whether you're recruiting
somebody for the agency or you're
recruiting somebody that's an enemy
asset, you kind of follow the same
procedure, right? Yes. You spot them,
you assess them, you assess their
vulnerabilities, you develop a
relationship, and then you ultimately
recruit them. It's the same procedure
whether you're doing it for the agency
or you're recruiting some terrorist that
you want to give you secrets. That's
exactly right.
That's exactly right. When you say
assess their vulnerabilities, what are
you looking for? Vulnerabilities are
probably the most important. And they're
not necessarily as awful as they might
seem. A vulnerability may be that a
person, you know, is a drunk or is a
drug addict or or hates his boss and is
is angry for being uh passed over for
promotion. But more commonly, a
vulnerability is this guy really loves
his children and he doesn't make very
much money. And at the CIA, we can get
your child enrolled in any university in
America, quite literally any university
in America, and the CIA will pay for it.
So if you want your child to go to
Harvard or Stanford or one guy asked
Strayer College, we'll do it.
Um, another vulnerability is uh somebody
who just really loves the United States.
I recruited a an agent one time who
would not take a single dollar from me
and didn't want any favors like a
college education for his children or
grandchildren. He just loved the United
States and he enjoyed the excitement,
the clandestinity of uh of meeting um
and then you know sometimes you'll get
somebody whose spouse has cancer or some
dread disease and by God you can get
them into the Mayo Clinic or the
Cleveland Clinic and and they'll give
you anything that you want so long as
you can you can provide medical care. So
that's what you're assessing in that in
that development. uh stage or the
assessment and development stage. What
can I give this person that is going to
make him want to give me what I want?
And how do you get them into the
university? How do you get them into say
Harvard or University of Texas or
wherever? How does the CIA do that? The
CIA has agreements with
uh just well every university almost
every university in America uh with
every you know Fortune 1000 or Fortune
1500 uh company in America and you know
university administrators and corporate
leaders they're they're patriots as well
and they want to do whatever they can to
be helpful. I I'll give you another
example. I I recruited a guy who was
absolutely crazy for the Chicago Bulls
and I got him a basketball autographed
by Michael Jordan. I just bought it at
at the, you know, the NBA store online
and had it shipped out to me. And I told
him, "Listen, you know, I know a guy who
knows a guy who knows Michael Jordan.
And we told Michael Jordan all about
you." and he autographed this basketball
and I put it in this acrylic box. He
couldn't give me the information I
wanted fast enough and he didn't take
any money for it. It was just because I
was so thoughtful, he said that I gave
him this basketball because I knew how
much he loved the Chicago Bulls. So, you
find what their currency is, what
they're interested in, and then you find
a way to get it to them. That's exactly
right. And money is not a particular
barrier when you're going after somebody
that the agency values.
No, no. I I'm smiling because we used to
have this saying that intelligence is a
cash business and cash is not a problem.
uh you know during during the
Afghanistan war in the very early days
of the Afghanistan war we were literally
throwing money out of the side of
helicopters and it led to this joke at
the agency that you can't buy an Afghan
warlord but you can certainly rent one
and that's what the agency did. So, if
they get a million dollars to rent a
warlord and it's cash, how do you know
they didn't rent them for 750 and keep
250? That is a great question. And I
will tell you, over the course of my
entire career, I never saw or heard of
anybody taking a single dollar. Again,
we're doing this out of a sense of
patriotism and duty. Now, when you're
meeting with a with a source and you
give him his monthly pay, which of
course is always in cash, he signs a
receipt and the receipt, it's perfectly
fine if he signs Mickey Mouse. He never
signs his real name. You tell him just
pick a name, stick with that name, and
uh you know, that's what he signs every
month. Uh but you're going to be
polygraphed on this, too. And they're
going to ask you, have you ever
misappropriated uh funds? I think the
question is, have you ever
misappropriated more than $20? That's
what they asked me on the polygraph. And
by God, you have to be able to say no.
And you have to be able to say it with a
clear conscience. So, they do check. Oh,
yeah. In fact, Dr. Phil, I remember uh
when we had a colleague of mine and I
were setting out to um to drive to
Fiselabad, Pakistan. This was about two
weeks before we captured Abu Zubeda. And
we had um $2 million in cash in the van
with us in two duffel bags. And my
colleague said, "You know, I could never
understand why people would cheat on
their on their accounting paperwork for
for 20 bucks or 30 bucks. What would
possess you to cheat the the CIA out of
20 bucks? If you're going to steal,
steal millions." And we looked at each
other and laughed. And I said, "Yeah, I
I wouldn't even steal the millions." and
he said, "No, neither would I." Yeah.
It' be a little hard to pass a polygraph
on that, right? That's right. But it's
not unfathomable for a highlevel source.
I know in Zero Dark 30 they have a scene
in there and they're trying to get a
source to come up with a phone number
and he wants a Lamborghini. So, they
just get him a Lamborghini in the middle
of the night. That's not far-fetched.
No. No. That's actually easy. You just
take a big sack of money over to the
Lamborghini dealership by the airport
and next thing you know, you've got a
Lamborghini. Yes. He's happy and you got
the phone number you want or the
information you want and moving on.
Exactly. Right. All it's all in the name
of the of the successful operation. All
of it. Yeah. I remember just after 911,
uh I I went up to Ambassador Black and I
said, "Kofheer, I wanted to talk to you
if you have a minute. I have an idea for
an operation." And before I could get
the words out of my mouth, he put his
hands up and he said, "Whatever it is,
just do it. I have so much money, I
can't possibly spend it all." And that
that continued for years after the 9/11
attacks.
Really? And where did that money come
from? Congress couldn't appropriate it
fast enough. Um, we were we were
receiving multibillion dollar
supplemental appropriations. So we had
our our fixed budget that that the
oversight committees had or the
appropriations committee had
appropriated and the oversight
committees had authorized and then
literally the day after 9/11 we got
something like 160% supplemental uh
appropriation and then got another one
again at the end of the year. We really
couldn't spend it all.